A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Program Office, Series 26 FA1205
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Program Office, Series 26
1958-1968
bulk 1963-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Draper, Edgar D.
FA1205
6.2 Cubic Feet 14 LGL sized Hollinger boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Scope and Contents
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains office files of Edgar D. Draper. They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series documents the activities of New York State Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's Program Office. It was created by Edgar D. Draper who served as Program Associate in Rockefeller's Executive Chamber. The contents of the series predominately concern education reform and development as well as national trends in Republican Party politics. Material formats include correspondence, memoranda, reports, press releases, pamphlets and other types of publications, newspaper clippings, copies of state and federal legislative bills, and transcripts of speeches and public addresses. In addition to Draper, chief correspondents found within the series include Secretary to the Governor Dr. William J. Ronan, Executive Officer to the Governor Alton G. Marshall, Commissioner of Education of the State of New York James E. Allen Jr., and Deputy Commissioner of Education Ewald B. Nyquist.
Arrangement
The series is arranged into 7 subseries. The subseries arrangement is as follows:
1. Political files, 1964-1966
2. Education files, 1959-1967
3. Insterstate Compact for Education,1965-1968
4. Long-Range Program Planning submisions, 1962-1966
5. Program planning preparations and follow-up, 1958-1966
6. Federal legislation, 1961-1966
7. Conference materials, 1963-1965
Biographical / Historical
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
Biographical / Historical
Edgar D. Draper served as Program Associate in New York State Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's Executive Chamber. He also represented the state of New York as a delegate at several meeting for the Interstate Compact for Education and its governing body, the Education Commission of the States.
Other Finding Aids
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360) Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by Happy Rockefeller.
Adult education and state; Civil rights; Civil service; Civil service -- New York (State); Education and state -- New York (State); Educational change; Federal government -- United States; Government aid to education -- New York (State); Government policy; Higher education and state; Interstate agreements; Legislation -- New York (State); Minorities -- Education (Higher) -- United States; Occupational training--United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political parties; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Program budgeting; Public policy; Science -- Study and teaching; Speeches, addresses, etc.; State governments -- United States; State universities and colleges; Tuition -- Education, Higher -- United States
- Political files, 1964-1966; 1; 1 Cubic Feet About 2.5 LGL sized Hollinger Boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The contents of the subseries primarily pertain to Nelson A. Rockefeller's political record and achievements as New York State Governor, the tensions and shifts within the Republican Party at the time of the 1964 Presidential Election, Rockefeller's meetings with New York town and county community leaders, and Rockefeller's discontinued run for the Republican Party nomination in the 1964 election. General political records include the correspondence of Program Associate Edgar D. Draper, lists of commitments made by Rockefeller in regards to the activities of various state programs, and transcripts of speeches and interviews by Rockefeller and other individuals. Many of the records discuss the relationship between the Republican Party and the African American community in connection to the Civil Rights Movement and the Republican Party's 1964 presidential candidate, Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater. The subseries includes a transcript of a public statement by Rockefeller in which he discusses the outcome of the election and calls for a constructive rebuilding of the party. Materials related to Rockefeller's various town and county visits throughout the state of New York include memoranda, schedules, lists of key community leaders, and reports providing background information and points of local interest for each meeting location. These documents are loosely organized by the town or county they concern. Records related to Rockefeller's run for Republican Party presidential nominee include correspondence, reports, statements, and pamphlets as well other miscellaneous campaign materials. Several documents originate from the campaigns of other nomination candidates as well as from the larger Republican Party platform. Lastly, the subseries contains a small amount of documents related to John V. Lindsay's campaign for New York City Mayor in 1965.
  - General political records, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General political records, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General political records, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John V. Lindsay New York City mayoral campaign white papers, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NAR town meetings, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5, 6, 7, 8)
    Towns and counties represented within this file include:
    1) Harlem; 2) Brooklyn; 3) Queens; 4) The Bronx; 5) City of Buffalo and Niagara and Erie Counties; 6) City of Syracuse and Onondaga County; 7) City of Utica and Oneida County; 8) Jamestown and Olean; 9) Albany; 10) City of Plattsburgh and Clinton County. Other miscellaneous towns and counties are also represented within the file.
    Separated Materials
    Materials separated from file pending relocation to flat file, reformatting, or preservation treatment:
    1) Fax about Syracuse public elementary schools - Folder 7 2) Fax about Utica public schools - Folder 7 3) Fax about Jamestown-Olean area - Folder 7 4) Fax about Anti-Poverty Program in Albany County - folder 8
  - NAR town meetings, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9, 10, 11, 12)
    Towns and counties represented wihtin this file include:
    1) Nassau and Suffolk Counties; 2) City of Binghampton and Broome County; 3) City of Buffalo and Erie County; 4) City of Rochester and Monroe County 5) Rockland and Westchester Counties. Other miscellaneous towns and counties are represented within the file.
    1) Fax about Rochester public elementary schools - Folder 11
  - NAR town meetings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13,14,15,16)
    1) St. Lawrence County; 2) Harlem; 3) Cortland and Tompkins Counties; 4) Montgomery, Fulton, and Monroe Counties; 5) Auburn, Newark, and Geneva; 6) Oswego and Jefferson Counties; 7) City of New York and Duchess and Ulster Counties; 7) Saratoga Springs and Glen Falls. Other miscellaneous towns and counties are also represented within the file.
    Materials separated from file pending relocation to flat file, reformatting, or preservation treatment include:
    1) Fax about Poughkeepsie and Kingston - Folder 15
  - NAR town meetings briefings, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17, 18, 19)
  - NAR United States presidential campaign correspondence and reports, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    File contains a letter addressed from Edgar D. Draper to retired Baseball player Jackie Robinson. The letter discusses the comments of several African American participants on David Susskind's television program "Open End" about the Republican Party. Draper asks Robinson if he thinks it is advisable to arrange a meeting where they can discuss suggested Republican Party outreach to the African American community. Robinson served as one of Nelson A. Rockefeller's national campaign directors for the 1964 Presidential Election.
    1) Virginian Pilot press clipping
  - NAR United States presidential campaign statements, brochures, and other promotional materials, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 21, 22, 23, 24)
    1) New York Times press clippings - Folder 21
- Education files, 1959-1967; 2; 1.5 Cubic Feet About 3.5 LGL sized Hollinger boxes
  This subseries documents matters related to New York State funding for education as well as to attempts at education reform and development by Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's Executive Chamber, the New York State Education Department, and other local, state, and national organizations concerned with education policy and institutions. Much of the education reform discussed in the subseries involves expansion of education opportunities to minority and disadvantaged populations, increased medical and health professional training in response to the state's Medicaid program, and improved programs for science and technology learning. Several files concern state and national education policy in a broad sense. These files include correspondence, reports, and other materials related to legislation and performance of state education programs, background information on the proposed Pennsylvania Plan property tax law, and multistate collaboration on education policy through the activities of the Interstate Compact for Education. A large part of the subseries specifically pertains to higher education policy and development with a particular focus on funding for the City University of New York. These materials include transcripts of addresses by various education and city officials before a Joint Legislative Committee on Education on March 22, 1966, CUNY budget information, correspondence concerning Rockefeller's support for the City University Supplementary Aid and Construction Bill, and a number of draft letters Program Associate Edgar D. Draper created when preparing Rockefeller's official responses to calls for greater state aid to CUNY. This subseries also includes tabulations of monetary amounts distributed by the state for college scholarships in the academic years 1958-1959 and 1964-1965.
  - General education program records, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General education program records, January 1966-April 1966 (Box 3, Folder 26, 27, 28)
    1) Faxes about nonwhite in-migrant pupils in New York City schools - Folder 27 2) Faxes about primary and secondary education and students that have migrated into the state - Folder 27
  - General education program records, May 1966-June 1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence and press releases related to adult education, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - NAR address before the New York State League of Women Voters, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - NAR statements on education, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 32, 33)
  - NAR statements on education, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - New York State education and departmental white papers, 1959-1966 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - New York State Joint Legislative Committee on Higher Education recommendations and statements, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - New York State Legislature Rules Report No. 595, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Appropriations and budget information related to City University of New York, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 38, 39)
  - Correspondence and reports related to City University of New York, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Materials separated from file pending relocation to flat-file, reformatting, or preservation treatment include:
    1) Fax about CUNY Income Fund Act
  - Draft NAR position statements and letter responses related to City University of New York, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Recommendations and statements related to City University of New York, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 42, 43)
  - Comparative tabulations for New York State aid for higher education, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 44, 45, 46)
    1) List of New York State cities and villages - Folder 45 2) Draft chart of state aid tabulations - Folder 45 3) Draft tabulations - Folder 46 4) College Master File - Folder 46 5) Draft list for tabulations - Folder 46
  - Correspondence related to tabulations for New York State aid for higher education, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - New York State Education Department correspondence and reports, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 48, 49, 50)
  - Correspondence and reports related to State University of New York, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - State University of New York Construction Fund models and sketches, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Materials separated from file for preservation treatment include:
    1) SUNY model renderings and sketches
    Conditions Governing Access
    Entire file is resticted until preservation actions are carried out on items.
  - Records related to higher education in general, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Records related to higher education in general, January 1966-June 1966 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Records related to health professionals' education, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Records related to medical education, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence and reports related to state and national education organizations, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 57, 58)
  - New York State Science and Technology Foundation correspondence, reports, and press releases, 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 59, 60)
  - New York State Science and Technology Foundation correspondence, reports, and press releases, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Records related to elementary and secondary education, general, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 62, 63)
  - Records related to elementary and secondary education, New York City public schools, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 64)
- Interstate Compact for Education, 1965-1968; 3; 1.25 Cubic Feet About 3 LGL sized Hollinger boxes
  This subseries documents the involvement of Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's administration in the origins and activities of the Interstate Compact for Education and its governing body, the Education Commission of the States. Much of the content found within the subseries pertains to different planning, interim, and annual meetings of the Compact and Commission. These records primarily consist of conference programs, reports, lists of attendees, meeting minutes, agendas, transcripts of addresses, and promotional materials related to both the actual meetings and the cities that hosted the meetings. The subseries also contains correspondence, press clippings, and transcripts of public speeches that relate to the Compact in a broader sense. The correspondence compiled by Rockefeller's Program Associate, Edgar D. Draper, chiefly concerns the list of delegates Rockefeller selected to represent the state of New York at different meetings of the Education Commission of the States. Lastly, the subseries contains several copies of the Compact for Education summary, copies of the Compact's Enabling Act, copies of New York State legislative bills related to the state joining the Compact, a copy of the Education Commission of the States Bylaws, and drafts and copies of other resolutions passed by the Compact.
  - General correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 65, 66, 67, 68)
    Materials separated from file pending relocation to flat file, reformatting, or preservaiton treatment include:
    1) Fax of draft letter to James E. Allen Jr. - Folder 68
  - Compact for Education Enabling Act and bills for New York State adoption, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 69, 70)
  - Education Commission of the States Bylaws and other Compact for Education resolutions, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Education Commission of the States publications and reports, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 72, 73)
    This file contains three publications printed by the Education Commission of the States:
    1) "Power Play for Control of Education" - a copy of the edited proceedings of the Commission's 1967 Annual Meeting; 2) Vol.1 No.7 of "Compact" - a monthly journal publication by the Commission; 3) "Seven Critical Issues in Education: Alternatives for State Action" - a collection of papers discussing education problems.
    This file also includes one summary report published by the New York State Department of Education about a multistate education conference that was titled "To Strengthen State-Local Relationships in Urban Education". Other types of documents such as correspondence and newspaper clippings were originally interspersed throughout the publications. They are currently housed with the publications with which they were originally attached.
  - Compact for Education Planning Conference, Kansas City, Missouri, lists and proceedings, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Compact for Education Planning Conference, Kansas City, Missouri, programs and promotion, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Compact for Education Planning Conference, Kansas City, Missouri, duplicates: Lists, agendas, and reports, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Compact for Education Planning Conference, Kansas City, Missouri, duplicates: Reports and addresses, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Compact for Education Interim Planning Meeting, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Education Commission of the States First Annual Meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Education Commission of the States First Annual Meeting, Chicago, Illinois, duplicates: Lists and addresses, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Education Commission of the States First Annual Meeting, Chicago, Illinois, duplicates: Minutes, resolutions, and recommended studies, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 81, 82)
  - Education Commission of the States Second Annual Meeting, Denver, Colorado, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 83, 84)
  - Education Commission of the States Steering Committee Meeting, Hilton Head, South Carolina, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 85, 86)
  - Education Commission of the States Third Annual Meeting, Denver, Colorado, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 87, 88)
  - Addresses and speeches related to Compact for Education, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Press clippings related to Compact for Education, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 90)
    Materials separated from this file pending relocation to flat file, reformatting, or preservation treatment include:
    1) Kansas City Times press clippings
  - Miscellaneous and duplicates, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 91, 92)
    File contains duplicates of items primarily found within the file "Compact for Education Enabling Act and bills for New York State adoption" as well as miscellaneous documents not found within the rest of the subseries. These documents chiefly relate to the operations of the Compact.
- Long-Range Program Planning submissions, 1962-1966; 4; .75 Cubic Feet About 2 LGL sized Hollinger boxes
  This subseries contains a small group of Long-Range Program Plans submitted by the New York State Commission for Human Rights, the New York State Education Department, and the New York State Division for Youth. According to the Guidelines and Instructions for Preparation of Long-Range Program Planning Submissions, agencies were required to compile this data in order to assist the New York State Division of the Budget in determining annual budget needs and in identifying the long-term impact of State programs. The Guidelines identify the expansion of state government and the developments in federal assistance programs as reasons for the need of a more systematic approach by the State in coordinating the program plans of individual agencies. A copy of these Guidelines, prepared by the Division of the Budget, is included with the subseries. Not all plans appear to be complete, but their individual components have been grouped together in the files in order to represent their contextual relationship.
  - Division of the Budget guidelines for Long-Range Program Planning submissions, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Commission for Human Rights, 1962-1965 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    In addition to the Long-Range Program Planning submission by the Commission for Human Rights, this file also contains a small pamphlet about New York State programs and legislation for advancing civil rights.
  - Education Department, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 95, 96, 97, 98, 99)
    File contains all Long-Range Programming Plans compiled for the year 1965
  - Education Department, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 100, 101, 102, 103, 104)
    File includes Long-Range Programming Plans for:
    1) Center on Innovation in Education; 2) Vocational Rehabilitation; 3) Elementary, Secondary, and Continuing Education; 4) Research and Evaluation; 5) Cultural Education and Special Services; 6) Regents Examination and Scholarships Center; 7) Educational Finance and Management Services.
  - Division for Youth, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 105, 106)
    File contains Long-Range Programming Plans for:
    1) Municipal Delinquency Prevention; 2) Facilities Program; 3) Research; 4) Administration; 5) Exhibits; 6) Departmental Summary
  - Division for Youth, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 107, 108)
    1) Administration and Research; 2) Facilitites Program; 3) Local Assistance Program.
- Program planning preparations and follow-up, 1958-1966; 5; .25 Cubic Feet About .5 LGL sized Hollinger box